John Dillenberger Papers
John Dillenberger Papers
1938-1994
Dillenberger, John.
9.25 linear ft.
Papers of the American theologian, author, Dean and President of the Graduate Theological Union, Berkeley, California. Collection includes correspondence, writings (articles, books, essays, reviews, speeches), memorabilia, and a draft of Paul Tillich's Systematic Theology with annotations by Dillenberger.
148941
Biographical History
John Dillenberger (1918–2008) was an American historian of science specializing in the relationship between science and religion. His book Protestant Thought and Natural Science (1960) was considered an authoritative introductory survey of the topic for several decades.
Dillenberger was one of the founders of the Graduate Theological Union in Berkeley, California, serving as its first president (he also served a second term in 1999-2000) and twice as dean (1964-1969 and 1967-1972). He was also actively involved in history and theology departments at several academic institutions, serving as president of Hartford Seminary, dean of the faculty at San Francisco Theological Seminary, chair of the program in history and philosophy at Harvard University, and president of the American Academy of Religion.
Paul Johannes Tillich (1886–1965) was a German-American theologian and Christian existentialist philosopher. He is considered by many to be one of the most influential Protestant theologians of the twentieth century.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Dillenberger Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and memorabilia.
Correspondence includes fellow authors and academics, particularly theologians and historians, from the Graduate Theological Union and other institutions. Notable individuals present in the collection include Bob Jones Jr., John W. Cook, David Daiches, Robert Lansing Edwards, Robert D. Funk, Theodore Gill, Mary Jean Irion, Margaret Ruth Miles, Robert Neville, Samuel I. Newhouse, Kenan Osborne, Paolo Ricca, Robert Scharlemann, Donald Shriver, Hannah Tillich, Jim Waits, J. Lynwood Walker, Barbara Wheeler, Wilson Yates, and others. There is also correspondence with religious, academic, and secular organizations with which Dillenberger was involved (Central Baptist Theological Seminary, First Congregational Church San Francisco, Graduate Theological Union, Interfaith Forum on Religion, Art, and Architecture, Princeton Theological Seminary, and the United Church of Christ), as well as publishers of both books and periodicals (Doubleday, MacMillan, etc.).
Writings by Dillenberger includes articles, book reviews, books, forewords, speeches, sermons, and address. Formats present include drafts, published editions, clippings, and reprints. There is also a copy of Dillenberger's PhD dissertation, "The Hidden God: A study of the concept of the hidden God in recent German theological works and the significance of this concept for contemporary theological thinking."
Writings by others consists of drafts of Paul Tillich's Systematic Theology, in the writing of which Dillenberger assisted Tillich. There is a complete draft of volume 1 plus fragments of other drafts. Revisions to the completed draft are Tillich's alone, while the fragments contain revisions by both Tillich and Dillenberger.
Memorabilia contains calendars, clippings, a few notes on administrative matters, invitations and programs from events attended by Dillenberger, honoraria, Dillenberger's Pastor's Manual from his time as a chaplain in the U.S. Naval Reserves, and assorted printed material including publicity for his books.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is alphabetical by correspondent name. Dillenberger's writings are subdivided by type; within that, they are arranged alphabetically by title.
Separated Material
A number of published items by Dillenberger and his wife Jane have been removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging, as follows. Please refer to to locate these items.
John Dillenberger, Contours of Faith: Changing Forms of Christian Thought, Abingdon Press, 1969
John Dillenberger, John Calvin: Selections from his Writings, Anchor Books, 1971
John Dillenberger, John Calvin: Selections from his Writings, Scholars Press, 1975
Perceptions of the Spirit in Twentieth-Century American Art, catalog from exhibit at Indianapolis Museum of Art prepared by Jane and John Dillenberger, 1977
Jane Dillenberger, The Hand and the Spirit: Religious Art in America, 1700-1900, University Art Museum, Berkeley, CA, 1972; introduction by John Dillenberger
Jane Dillenberger, Secular Art with Sacred Themes, Abingdon Press, 1969
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and philosophy; Science and medicine; Church and clergy; Adams, James Luther, 1901-1994.; Dillenberger, John.; Dillenberger, Jane.; Funk, Robert W. (Robert Walter), 1926-2005.; Gill, Theodore A. (Theodore Alexander), 1920-2005.; Irion, Mary Jean.; Jones, Bob, 1911-1997.; McCarter, Neely Dixon, 1929-; Miles, Margaret R. (Margaret Ruth), 1937-; Newhouse, Samuel Irving, Jr., 1927-2017.; Pauck, Wilhelm, 1901-1981.; Pelikan, Jaroslav, 1923-2006.; Ricca, Paolo.; Rosen, James M., 1933-; Scharlemann, Robert P.; Smith, Huston.; Tillich, Hannah.; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965. -- Systematic theology.; Weizsäcker, Carl Friedrich, Freiherr von, 1912-2007.; Wheeler, Barbara G.; Yates, Wilson.; Graduate Theological Union.; Hamma School of Theology.; Harvard University.; United Church of Christ.; Christianity and the arts.; Educators -- United States.; Protestantism -- History.; Religion and science.; Religion and the humanities.; Religious thought -- Modern period, 1500-; Theology -- 20th century.; Theology -- Study and teaching.; Theology, Doctrinal--Historical.; Theologians -- United States.; Calendars.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts.; Manuscripts for publication.; Programs.; Invitations.; Essays.; Reviews (documents); Speeches (documents); Educators.; Theologians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Dillenberger, 1969-1994.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Abingdon Press, 1966-1969; 1978,; 1990 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Doug and Margo [GTU], 1978; 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - Adams, James Luther, 1984; 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Religion (AAR), 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - American Theological Society, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Apostolos-Cappadona, Diane [professor; member of AAR], 1984-1989; 1993; 1 letter in German (Box 1)
  - Archives of American Art, 1975; 1981,; 1985-1992,; undated (Box 1)
  - A, misc (Box 1)
  - Barr, Robert [president, GTU], 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Baumgarten, Barbara Dee, 1991-1993; undated (Box 1)
  - Berling, Judith [dean, GTU], 1987-1993 (Box 1)
  - Biblical Archaeology Society, 1986; 1988 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Livingston [Ludlow Jr.] [National Endowment for the Arts], 1980 (Box 1)
  - Blecker, Michael [president, GTU; president, Saint John's University in Minnesota], 1981; 1983,; 1987 (Box 1)
  - Bucher, Glenn [president, GTU], 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - B, misc (Box 1)
  - Carson, David E.A. and Sara [bank president; involved with both Hartford Seminary and GTU], 1980-1982; 1989-1990,; undated (Box 1)
  - Central Baptist Theological Seminary, 1987; 1993 (Box 1)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1955; 1981-1982,; 1985 (Box 1)
  - Cherry, Conrad, 1979-1981; 1985,; 1987 (Box 1)
  - The Christian Century, 1969; 1987,; 1989 (Box 1)
  - Cook, John W. [professor, Yale; president, Henry Luce Foundation], 1979; 1987,; 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - C, misc (Box 1)
  - Daiches, David [Scottish author], 1979; 1987 (Box 1)
  - DeConcini, Barbara [Archives of American Art], 1990-1993; undated (Box 1)
  - Dempsey, Terrence [founding director of St. Louis University MOCRA], 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1985-1986; 1991 (Box 1)
  - Devonshire Jones, Tom [pastor at St. Mark's, Regent's Park, London], 1988; 1992-1993,; undated; wife Susan (Box 1)
  - Dillenberger, Jane [first wife], 1989; 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    See also Miscellaneous, personal.
  - Doubleday & Company, 1968-1971; 1974,; 1981-1983,; 1988 (Box 1)
  - Drew University, 1953-1954; 1962,; 1992 (Box 1)
  - du Plessix-Gray, Francine, See Gray, Cleve.
  - Duke, James. O., 1985-1987; undated (Box 2)
  - Duke University, 1950; 1982 (Box 2)
  - D, misc (Box 2)
  - Edwards, Robert Lansing [minister, author], 1982; 1987-1988,; 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Elberg, Sanford [UC Berkeley], 1987-1988; 1990,; 1992 (Box 2)
  - Emory University, 1987 (Box 2)
  - E, misc (Box 2)
  - Feinstein, Dianne, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, 1991-1993; undated (Box 2)
  - Fink, Lois Marie, 1982; 1984,; 1987-1988,; 1993 (Box 2)
  - [First Congregational Church, San Francisco], 1984-1987 (Box 2)
  - Funk, Robert D. [Westar Institute, divinity denier], 1982; 1986,; 1988,; undated; includes letters to his wife, Charlene Matejovsky (Box 2)
  - Furniss, Carl T. [Board member, Hartford Seminary], 1981; 1983,; 1987 (Box 2)
  - F, misc (Box 2)
  - Gerhart, Mary, See Yu, Anthony C.
  - Gill, Theodore [one of the founders of GTU], 1962-1963; 1979,; 1982,; 1986,; 1991-1993,; undated (Box 2)
  - Gottwald, Norman K., 1979 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Theological Union (GTU), 1963; 1970-1971,; 1982-1989,; 1991-1993,; undated (Box 2)
  - Gray, Cleve [artist], 1979; 1981,; 1986-1987,; 1993,; undated; includes his wife, author Francine du Plessix-Gray (Box 2)
  - G, misc (Box 2)
  - Hamma School of Theology, See Wittenberg University, Hamma School of Theology
  - Harper & Row, 1968; 1975,; 1987 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Seminary, 1977; 1980-1983,; 1989,; undated (Box 2)
  - Harvard University, 1954-1957; 1983,; 1985; includes letter in German (Box 2)
  - Hatfield, Mark O. [US Senator], 1989 (Box 2)
  - Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Hubbard, David Allen [Fuller Theological Seminary], 1987 (Box 2)
  - Hummel, Gert [German theologian], 1988; includes letter in German (Box 2)
  - H, misc (Box 2)
  - Indiana, Robert [artist], 1979; 1985 (Box 3)
  - Interfaith Forum on Religion, Art, and Architecture (IFRAA), 1984-1985; 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Irion, Mary Jean [poet, religious writer], 1985; 1987 (Box 3)
  - I, misc (Box 3)
  - Jones, Bob Jr. [president, Bob Jones University], 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Judd, Raymond [chaplain, Trinity University, San Antonio, TX], 1984; 1988,; 1992 (Box 3)
  - J, misc (Box 3)
  - Kegley, Charles W., 1969; 1981,; 1986 (Box 3)
  - Kenney, Scott G. [Sunstone magazine], 1979; 1993 (Box 3)
  - K, misc (Box 3)
  - Lilly Endowment, 1981-1982; 1984,; 1986-1988,; 1990,; 1993 (Box 3)
  - L, misc (Box 3)
  - Macmillan Publishing Company, 1985; 1987 (Box 3)
  - Matejovsky, Charlene, name misspelled by Dillenberger as "Mategeovsky" (Box 3)
    See also Funk, Robert D. (her husband)
  - McCarter, Neely D. [Pacific School of Religion], 1986-1988; 1990 (Box 3)
  - Meier, Richard [architect], 1984; 1993 (Box 3)
  - Mighetto, Frank L. [architect], 1985 (Box 3)
  - Miles, Margaret Ruth [theology educator, associated with Harvard and GTU], 1985-1987; 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - M, misc (Box 3)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1975; 1977,; 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Negri, Pat [Australian Catholic priest with PhD from GTU], 1991-1993 (Box 3)
  - Neville, Robert Cummings [professor, Boston University], 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - New York Times, 1969; 1985,; undated (Box 3)
  - Newhouse, Samuel Irving Jr., 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Niebuhr, Ursula Mary (Mrs. Reinhold Niebuhr), 1969; 1971 (Box 3)
  - Osborne, Kenan B. [Catholic priest, scholar], 1973-1974; undated (Box 3)
  - N-O, misc (Box 3)
  - Pacala, Leon [administrator, Association of Theological Schools], 1985; 1987,; 1989 (Box 3)
  - Pacific School of Religion, 1977; 1990 (Box 3)
  - Pauck, Wilhelm and Marion [historical theologian], 1981; 1992,; undated (Box 3)
  - Pelikan, Jaroslav [Yale theologian], 1986 (Box 3)
  - Princeton Theological Seminary, 1950; 1985,; 1988-1989,; 1991 (Box 3)
  - P, misc (Box 3)
  - Quinn, Patrick J. [architect and dean of RPI's School of architecture], 1979-1981; 1993 (Box 3)
  - Rambusch, Robert E. [artist, liturgical designer], 1982; 1991,; undated (Box 3)
  - Ricca, Paolo [Italian theologian and author], 1985-1987; 1990,; 1992,; undated (Box 3)
  - Rion, Michael [Hartford Seminary], 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Rosen, James [artist], 1990; 1993 (Box 3)
  - R, misc (Box 3)
  - "Saint Peter's Church", 1977-1980; relating to efforts to build an arts center (Box 4)
  - Scharlemann, Robert P. [theologian], 1979-1980; 1988,; 1993 (Box 4)
  - Schmookler, Andrew Bard [author, speaker], 1979-1980; 1982 (Box 4)
  - Scholars Press, 1978-1980; 1989,; 1993 (Box 4)
    See also Cherry, Conrad.
  - Scott, Nathan A. Jr. [professor of religion], 1985-1986; 1990,; 1992 (Box 4)
  - Seeberg, L., 1958; includes memorial booklet about Bengt Seeberg, sailor who sank with the German battleship Tirpitz in 1944; in German (Box 4)
  - Shaw, Nancy Rivard, See Detroit Insitute of Arts.
  - Shriver, Donald W. Jr. [president, Union Theological Seminary], 1982 (Box 4)
  - Smith, Huston [professor, Syracuse University], 1993 (Box 4)
  - Society for the Arts, Religion, and Contemporary Culture (ARC), 1985-1989 (Box 4)
  - Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - Staley, Allen [art historian], 1977-1979 (Box 4)
  - Stern, Robert A.M. [architect], 1986 (Box 4)
  - S, misc, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Tillich, Hannah (Mrs. Paul Tillich), 1979; 1987 (Box 4)
  - Tremaine, Emily Hall and Burton, 1979; 1981 (Box 4)
  - Trinity University Press, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Tuchman, Maurice [art curator], 1987 (Box 4)
  - Tyree, Alan D., 1987-1989; discussion of artistic matters for the Mormon Temple Project (Box 4)
  - T, misc (Box 4)
  - "United Church Architecture", 1972; 1978-1983; letters, notes, pamphlets, etc. relating to architectural matters (Box 4)
  - "United Church of Christ", 1984-1985; mostly related to architecture (Box 4)
  - "United Church of Christ", 1970-1981; mostly related to higher education issues (Box 4)
  - "United Church of Christ", 1979-1982; mostly related to higher education issues (Box 5)
  - Voisin, Carol Jean [ethicist and university administrator], 1987-1988; 1991,; 1993 (Box 5)
  - Waits, Jim L. [dean, Candler School of Theology, Emory University], 1985; 1987,; 1991,; 1993 (Box 5)
  - Walker, J. Lynwood [president, Northwest Theological Union], 1986; 1988,; 1990 (Box 5)
  - Weizsäcker, Carl Friedrich von [physicist], 1961; in German (Box 5)
  - Welch, Claude [GTU], 1972; 1977,; 1982,; 1986,; 1988,; undated (Box 5)
  - Wheeler, Barbara G. [president, Auburn Theological Seminary, Auburn NY], 1984-1985; 1990 (Box 5)
  - Wiggins, James, 1985-1986; 1988-1991,; 1993,; undated (Box 5)
  - Willems, Loretta, 1989-1990; 1992 (Box 5)
  - Winquist, Charles Edwin [professor of religion, Syracuse University and Chico State], 1979; 1985 (Box 5)
  - Wittenberg University, Hamma School of Theology, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
  - W, misc (Box 5)
  - Yates, Wilson [theologian and academic], 1982; 1988,; 1992,; undated (Box 5)
  - Yu, Anthony C. [professor of religion and literature, University of Chicago], 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Y-Z, misc (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, first name only (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, personal
    - "Hilde", 1962-1964; 1967,; undated; letters relating to Dillenberger's divorce from his first wife Hilde, including one to their children (Box 5)
    - "That Peace", 1962; letters relating to Dillenberger's marriage to his second wife Jane; departure from Drew University; includes a letter to his parents (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Art and Architecture in the Religious Community, Fall 1980; Faith & Form, entire issue; photocopy of article; New Conversations (Box 5)
    - Artists and Church Commissions: Rubin's 'The Church at Assy' Revisited, Spring 1979; Art Criticism, entire issue; photocopy of article (Box 5)
    - Barth's Letter in America, Dec 1941; editorial, The Union Review; entire issue (Box 5)
    - Bela Vasady, Bridge-Builder Between East and West, Jul 5, 1949; The Messenger (Box 6)
    - The Catholic -Protestant Opening, winter 1964; Season, entire issue (Box 6)
    - The Church and Society, winter 1945; Christianity and Society, entire issue (Box 6)
    - Christianity Not the Only Option, Mar 4, 1954; The Christian Scholar, a collection of essays entitled "A Symposium: Can and Should a College be Christian?"; reprint (Box 6)
    - Christianity, Science and Truth, May 1949; Perspective: A Princeton Journal of Christian Opinion, entire issue (Box 6)
    - Church Union: Theology and Culture, Oct 1962; Theology Today (Box 6)
    - The Diversity of Disciplines as a Theological Question: the Visual Arts as a Paradigm, typescript copy and pages from the Journal of the American Academy of Religion, v.48 no.2 (Box 6)
    - [Encyclopedia entries, miscellaneous] (Box 6)
    - English Christianity and the Visual Arts in the Colonies, Semeia 13, entire issue (Box 6)
    - Faith, typescript copy of item eventually published in New Handbook of Christian Theology; correspondence with Joseph L. Price, coordinator of the project (Box 6)
    - Faith and Sensibility, fall 1978; Journal of Current Social Issues, entire issue; also includes an article by Jane Dillenberger (Box 6)
    - From a Persecuted Church [co-written by Dillenberger and Cedric H. Jaggard], Mar 1941; The Union Review, entire issue (Box 6)
    - From the World of the Artists to the Museum World: Its Implications for Tillich's Views of the Visual Arts, typescript (Box 6)
    - God the Creator, Dec 1952; Counsel (Box 6)
    - Grace and Works in Martin Luther and Joseph Smith, May/Jun 1978; Sunstone, entire issue; photocopied pages (Box 6)
    - The Graduate Theological Union in the San Francisco Bay Area, Jan 1965; The Journal of Bible and Religion, reprints (Box 6)
    - The Graduate Theological Union: Seven Years Later, spring 1969; Nexus, entire issue; photocopied pages (Box 6)
    - GTU Aspirations Are Set Forth by Head of School, Jan 1965; Pacific Churchman, photocopy (Box 6)
    - History and the Kingdom of God, Jan/Mar 1954; Counsel, photocopy (Box 6)
    - The Holy Spirit Outside the Church, Jun 1958; The Bulletin of the Hartford Seminary Foundation, entire issue (Box 6)
    - I Go to War as a Christian, May 16, 1944; The Messenger, clipping and photocopy (Box 6)
    - The Integration of Theological Faculties, Apr 1969; Concilium, 2 typescript copies; clipping; reprints of translations in Dutch, French, German, Italian, and Spanish (Box L 10)
    - Introduction to Tillich's Theology, autumn 1951; The Drew Gateway, entire issue, clipping (Box 6)
    - Judaism and Protestantism: Some Historic Patterns of Understanding, Sep-Oct 1966; "corrected copy," photocopy of typescript manuscript given at colloquium (Box 6)
    - Justification and Sanctification, May 1943; The Union Review, entire issue (Box 6)
    - The Landmarking of Religious Institutions: a Plea for Vision with Wider Contexts, fall 1984; Faith & Form, photocopy of clipping (Box 6)
    - Luther and the Communication of Christianity to Culture, typescript (Box 6)
    - Major Volumes and Selected Periodical Literature in Luther Studies, 1956-1959, Mar 1961; Church History, reprint (Box 6)
    - Man and the World, Jun 3, 1959; The Christian Century, entire issue (Box 6)
    - Modern Art and its Relation to Christianity, circa 1938; typescript of term paper from Eisenhower College (Box 6)
    - Nature vs. Biblical Literalism, May 20, 1959; The Christian Century, entire issue (Box 7)
    - Notes From a Theological Perspective, Nov 1963; Social Action, entire issue; photocopy of pages (Box 7)
    - Paul Tillich: Theologian of Culture, 1966; 1967; two different articles with the same title: Challenge: A Theological Journal for the Probing of the Mind, Feb 1966, typescript with holograph corrections; Religion in Life, winter 1966, reprint (Box 7)
    - Perceptions of the Spirit in Twentieth Century American Art, May 1978; American Art Review, entire issue; photocopy of pages (Box 7)
    - A Protestant Understanding of the Church and University, June 17-21, 1962; address from 3rd Quadrennial Convocation of Christian Colleges at St. Olaf College, Northfield, Minnesota; in booklet, "The Mission of the Christian College in the Modern World" published by the Council of Protestant Colleges and Universities (Box 7)
    - Protestantism in the United States. Its Temper and Main Tendencies., 1961; Studium Generale, 14 Jahrg., Heft 2, reprint (Box 7)
    - Reflections of a Protestant Champlin, May 1946; Union Seminary Quarterly Review, entire issue (Box 7)
    - Religious Sensibilities: The Conceptual and Visual, June 8, 1978; address given at New Orleans Religion & the Arts Conference; includes booklet (Box 7)
    - Religious Stimulants and Constraints in the Development of Science, spring 1967; Continuum, clipping (Box 7)
    - Roots of the American Ethos, 1978; photocopied pages from book, Understanding the New Religions, Seabury Press (Box 7)
    - Science and Theology Today, Jun 17, 1959; fall 1959; 2 versions, one in The Christian Century, the other with a handwritten title that could be "Satellite" (Box 7)
    - The Seductive Power of the Visual Arts: Shall the Response be Iconoclasm or Baptism?, Mar 1977; Jan 1978; Andover Newton Quarterly, photocopy; reprint from Liturgy (Box 7)
    - The Society for the Arts Religion and Contemporary Culture, Jun 1988; ARTS, entire issue (Box 7)
    - The Sovereignty of God in John Calvin and Brigham Young Response, Sep/Oct 1980; Sunstone, entire issue (Box 7)
    - Teaching Religion: Problems and Requirements, Mar 1954; Union Theological Seminary Quarterly Review, reprint with pencil comments (Box 7)
    - Theological-Cultural Factors Demanding Union of the Churches, Jun 1963; typescript; clipping from Mid-stream (Box 7)
    - "Theological Education", 1969; first draft typescript with handwritten corrections (Box 7)
    - Theological Givens as Theological Orientations, 1967; Mid-stream,clipping; second copy titled "Cambridge Background Paper No.1 prepared at the request of the Executive Committee as a background paper for the 1967 meeting of the Consultation on Church Union" (Box 7)
    - Theological Hermeneutics, typescript with handwritten corrections; handwritten note indicates appeared in New Frontiers of Theology vol II (Box 7)
    - Theology and Abstract Expressionism. Historical Notes and Test Cases., 4 typescript copies with handwritten corrections (Box 7)
    - Theology and Ethos: the Making and Breaking of Cultural Styles, typescript with handwritten corrections (Box 7)
    - Tillich's Use of the Concept of "Being", Mar 16, 1953; Christianity and Crisis, clipping (Box 7)
    - Traditional Library Functions and the Economic Factor, autumn 1969; typescript draft with handwritten corrections; photocopy of pages from Theological Education (Box 7)
    - Unraveling the Library Mystique, autumn 1980; Theological Education, entire issue (Box 7)
    - Visual Arts. The Discipline of Seeing [on article page, but table-of-contents has as "The Visual Arts in Worship"], Dec/Jan 1978; Modern Liturgy, entire issue (Box 7)
    - What is Christian Art? [by Jane and John Dillenberger], Apr 20, 1966; The Christian Century, entire issue (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous drafts (Box 7)
  - Book reviews
    - Miscellaneous, 1946; 1950-1963,; 1972,; 1984-1988,; 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Books
    - Contours of Faith: Changing Forms of Christian Thought
      - Draft A, typescript with holograph corrections; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Draft B, typescript with holograph corrections; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Draft C, typescript with holograph corrections; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Draft D, typescript with holograph corrections; 2 folders (Box 8)